What I've set up here is a simple
demonstration of combustion.
Not to be undertaken without
supervision, mind. Without oxygen, the
suffocated and cannot burn.
The larger the jar, the more oxygen the
candle has to consume.
Therefore, the longer the flame will
burn.
Who can explain why a flame needs oxygen
to burn?
Fire! Raise your hand before you speak,
Mr. King.
But, sir!
No buts. If you have anything to say,
raise your hand.
Well, Mr. King.
But, sir, there's a fire outside!
I want you all to stay in your seats.
Don't want it to go anywhere near the
fire.
Come on.
Let's have
another
relay, man.
Got fire inside.
Fire's out.
Just a lot of smoke left.
How'd it happen?
I don't know. I just stepped out for
some supplies, and the next thing I
everybody was yelling fire.
Looks like some kerosene rags got too
close to the floor.
It's a good thing you got here as
quickly as you did. The whole place
gone up.
Well, it was Felix who spotted the
smoke.
Mr. Pettibone.
Don't exaggerate, Felix, especially with
your mouth full.
We should be glad no one got hurt.
Well, if it wasn't for Mr. Pettibone,
Prince would have been lost in the
He practically put the fire out single
-handedly.
You should have seen him. He was very
heroic.
Well, it seems to me that there were a
lot of other people helping out besides
your teacher.
Mr. Pettibone said if it wasn't for me
seeing the smoke, the box in the shop
would have burned to the ground.
Oh, what a terrible thought.
Maybe next time we won't be so lucky.
That's a good point.
What are you thinking?
Well, maybe it's time that Avonlea got
its own fire department.
A real fire department?
It was just loose.
I tightened it up.
Mr. Pettibor.
Oh, I, uh, told Hedy I'd come by and fix
it. There was no need for you to drive
out this way. No bother.
Good day, Mr. King.
Attention, everyone.
Thank you.
As the acting chairman of the town
council, I would like to bring this
to order.
The floor is now open.
Well, I was thinking... Alec, please
raise your hand if you want the floor.
The chair recognizes Alec King.
Well, after that fire at the blacksmith
shop, it seems to me it would be a good
idea for us to have our own fire
department.
What a wonderful idea.
Please, everyone, let's keep the meeting
in order, one at a time.
The chair recognizes Clara Potts.
A fire department sounds fine and well,
but who is going to pay for it?
She's got a point, you know. A fire
department won't come cheap. And what
all that equipment?
and hooks and ladders, a hose wagon.
Won't that cost a lot?
And we'd have to build some kind of
firehouse, too.
If I may make another suggestion...
Alec, you're out of turn. Please raise
hand.
The chair recognizes Alec King.
Well, I had in mind a volunteer fire
department.
Oh, well, that's a bit different.
Would volunteering be mandatory for
everyone?
If it was mandatory, it would not be a
volunteer fire department, Bert.
Well, the chair recognizes Mr.
Pettibone.
I'd just like to lend my support to Mr.
King's suggestion.
For a community our size, a volunteer
fire department would be a cost
and practical solution to our
firefighting needs and bring a greater
security to the people of Avonlea.
Well said.
And I agree with Mr. Pettibone.
A volunteer fire department may be just
what Avonlea needs.
I move that Avonlea establish its own
volunteer fire department.
Is there a seconder?
Seconded by Archie Gillis. All in favor?
It's unanimous.
Avonlea will have its very own volunteer
fire department.
Now that we've decided to have a fire
department, what do we do next?
Are we going to have uniforms?
You can't be a proper fireman without a
uniform.
You're going to fight fires, not parade
around town.
I think what we have to discuss here is
just what equipment we need.
Mr. King has a point.
Well, where do we begin?
I've got a good axe I can loan.
I've got 100 feet of mountain climbing
rope I don't need. We'll need a tall
ladder. You can borrow your layly
bugles.
Do you mean that old ladder out the back
of her house?
Well, it's all warped, and it's missing
at least three rungs.
Well, then, you can fix it, Bert, can't
you? What about a firefighting wagon?
Without that, we'll be no better off
than we are now.
Well, I have an old field irrigation
wagon with a 250 -gallon tank, which I
haven't used for years, and with a good
pump and some hose, I think it could be
converted into a horse -drawn fire
wagon.
It'd be a little primitive, and you'd
have to get enough water pressure in the
hose, but it could work.
Splendid, Mr. Pettibone.
So Avonlea will have its own fire
department, and thanks to Alec King, its
homemade firefighting wagon.
Well,
perhaps the, uh...
Good to see such an impressive turnout
for our first training session.
When are we going to get our uniforms?
I think maybe before we discuss the
uniforms, we should do a few drills.
Maybe we should do some exercises first.
Calisthenics? Yeah, that's it,
calisthenics.
Form two opposing ranks.
Everyone ready?
And...
and then come to attention. Put your
arms over your heads and touch your
Put your arms over your heads again.
Archie! Archie! Are you all right?
I think I pulled a muscle.
Come on, then.
Maybe we should just move on to a few
drills.
It's easy when you get the hang of it.
So who's going to be first?
Archie.
What do you say? Give it a try.
Hey, come on, Archie. There's nothing to
be afraid of. I don't see you stepping
to the front of the line.
Oh, no, he's moaning about it. Here.
Let's give it a go.
Oh, yeah.
Oh, this is the easiest falling off
horse.
Uncle Alec!
What's wrong?
There's been an accident.
It's Felix.
Felix? What kind of accident?
All right, calm down. Where is he? He's
in the kitchen.
Oh, good.
I'll be right down.
Wait.
What problem here?
Felix.
I didn't do anything.
It's true, Uncle Alex.
It was Izzy.
Izzy?
They were going to play Man in the Iron
Mask.
Oh, I get the idea.
Somebody do something!
I can't get it on!
I don't find this very amusing, Mr.
Pettibone. Sorry.
There's no buts about it. What do you
think you were doing, Izzy?
Now, wait a minute, King. You can't talk
to my daughter in that tone of voice.
Well, maybe if you did, she wouldn't
behave like a wild savage.
She might be a little high -spirited.
High -spirited? She's a minute. Now, you
just hold on there, son. I know.
We could stand him on his head and shake
him by the ankles.
Don't be daft, Bert.
We'll haul him up by his ankles, over
the barn beam, then fill up the bucket
with water until it falls off.
Don't scare the boy, Archie. Be a man,
Felix.
Don't you tell my son what he should be.
Your daughter could use a little old
-fashioned discipline.
Don't you presume to tell me how to
raise my own child, Mr. Kane.
This is no time to be arguing. I'm not
arguing, but no one here is coming up
with a reasonable suggestion.
How'd you... A good swift yank.
Oh, that man
really irritates me, Janet. Oh, that
hurts.
Sorry, dear.
Well... Tied pettibone can be rather
prickly, but... You don't need to tell
Janet, have you noticed that he spends a
lot of time at Hedy's?
I suppose he has school matters to
discuss.
Oh, well, King.
You're not for a second suggesting that
you're a sister.
It's no laughing matter, Janet. He's a
worldly man. He was in the military, for
heaven's sake.
Oh, well.
I think you're letting your imagination,
your own dislike for the man, color
your judgment.
Hetty's an intelligent and capable
woman.
I suppose you're right. Of course I am.
Well, thank you.
I'd rather get to work on that
irrigation wagon.
Mr. Kang.
Ah, Gus.
So, you making much progress?
Well, it's got a lot more holes in it
than I remember, but she's still in
good shape.
Looks like I spoke too soon.
Mr.
Kang, I'd like to volunteer for the new
fire brigade.
Huh? Well, it's not like I know anything
about fighting the fires and all, but I
just hate to see a place as beautiful as
Avonlea go up in flames.
I know what you mean, Gus.
I appreciate your concern.
You know, I sit in the lighthouse there
and see for miles, and it's all so
beautiful.
And it's become my home.
Now, there's an idea.
What's that?
Well, you've got a bird's -eye view of
Avonlea from that lighthouse.
You could be our first fire scout.
Fire scout?
Well, Avonlea, so spread around, you've
got the perfect spot to see smoke from a
fire from just about anywhere.
But I'm so far from town.
How would I give the word?
Yeah, well, we'd have to get you a bell.
I know, the old church bell.
It's been lying around for years
collecting dust. I'm sure we could get
Well, what do you say?
Are you ready to be Avonlea's first
volunteer fire scout?
That's okay.
That would be an honor.
Hello, Gus.
Oh, hello, Felicity.
Mother thought you might be chilled, so
I brought you some hot chocolate.
Oh, thank you. Did you use something
warm?
I saw you heading over, Gus, so I
brought some for you, too.
Oh, thank you.
How does this work, Father?
Oh, well, I'm, uh...
I'm going to rig up a pump to it, fix a
fire hose onto where the drainage pipe
was, and with any luck at all, I'll have
enough pressure to throw the water 50
feet or so.
Really?
Your father said I could be a fire
scout.
Isn't that dangerous?
I don't think so.
I'll just be looking for fires from the
lighthouse, and when I see one, I'll
just ring my fire bell.
That's a very big responsibility, Gus.
watching out for the safety of everyone
in the community.
I never thought about it like that.
Oh, you won't let us down, Gus.
I know you're the right man for the job.
I don't think Eulalie Bugle's ladder is
worth using.
You try telling that to Mr. Bugle. Come
on, boys, that's not a fireman's
attitude.
Maybe he could use a little work.
Well, that's what we're here for, isn't
it?
I'm all for fixing the ladder if that
means we don't have to do those darn
drills.
If you've got a scale of burning
building to save someone's life, maybe
your own, you'll think differently about
the drills.
Easy, Mr. Pettipone. It's just Archie's
sense of humor.
I see.
By the way, I appointed Gus Pike to be
one of our fire scouts. I thought we
could put a bell at the lighthouse.
Don't you think you should have
discussed it with us first?
I didn't think there was any harm in it.
How do you know Gus Pike can take on
such a responsibility? Besides, the
lighthouse is so far from town. You've
only known Gus Pike for a short while in
a classroom.
He's been managing that lighthouse for
two years, and he's done an excellent
job, and he'll be one of our fire
scouts.
Sounds to me like Gus can do the job.
It's not a matter of whether he can do
job. It's a question of procedure, and I
think you've overstepped your authority
by appointing Gus without consulting us.
You mean without discussing with you.
Consequently, I can't decide if Paulina
should fall in love with this mysterious
stranger.
What do you think?
Mr. Pettibone, you've not been listening
to a word I've said.
I'm sorry.
I take it there's something on your
mind.
It's your brother.
He doesn't seem to like me. I don't know
why.
Not like you.
Ridiculous. He hardly knows you.
He certainly seems to think he does.
Oh, well, that's different.
Why, with all the time we've spent
together in the past two months, I can't
I know you all that well either.
Am I that difficult?
Well, it's only when I see you with your
children, really, that I think I can
see the real you, if you'll pardon the
expression.
Seems to me you're not as much of a
gruff as you'd have us think you are.
Speaking of the children, I've got to
get to the schoolhouse before they start
to arrive.
I don't want to set a bad example.
Oh, no.
Morning, Hattie.
Morning, Alec. I'm in the kitchen.
Oh, here, let me help you with that.
No, I can manage.
No, it'll be easier if you let me. I can
manage, Alec.
Oh,
I'm sorry.
I just wanted to help.
Oh, I see.
Thank you.
I came by to see if my spanner was here
anywhere. I couldn't find it in the
barn.
Spanner?
I haven't seen your spanner.
Well, usually I leave it in the box
here, but this morning it was nowhere to
seen, and I... How stupid of me. It was
here at the bottom.
Oh, well, good then. You found it.
Well, I'd better get back to work.
Sorry to have bothered you.
Oh, by the way, how are things at
school?
School?
Well, with Mr. Pettibone keeping you
informed, you must know how things are
going. Oh, well, very well, in fact.
How do you find Mr. Pettibone?
He's a good teacher.
What a question.
To be sure the students respect him
and... Not too pushy or overbearing?
Heavens, no.
Why ever do you ask such a thing?
Well, he's no saint. We all have our
faults. He must have his.
I wouldn't know, would I? Well, you do
seem to spend a lot of time together.
Because school matters mainly.
Curriculum and so on.
I think that's a personal need.
I see.
Why do you ask, Alec?
Oh,
no reason. Just curious.
But the sun had already come up.
So there we were, trying to put out the
fire while bullets were flying over our
heads. Oh, my. I have to admit, I
thought we were going to lose that one.
Hard to imagine you got out of that
alive.
Sorry I'm late, fellas.
You should have been here earlier, hear
Clive tell some of his war stories.
Did you know that Clive was in the
military fire brigade?
No, no, I didn't.
Well, I guess we'd better get to work.
We've got all this paraphernalia to sort
through.
Where did it come from? People have been
dropping off since we started.
I don't know what's any good.
Some of it's pretty old.
You must have thought the count.
Alec!
There's a fire. You've got to hurry.
Calm down, Elvira. Where is it?
Bert. Bert, your house is on fire.
What? My house?
All right, let's go then. Load the wagon
first.
Spring the bucket.
Mrs. Bugler.
Tell it myself.
Then we've got two emergencies.
What do we do now? Well, burst closer.
We'll head there, work on that, and send
someone over to Mrs. Bugler's and see
how bad it is.
The Bugler's house is in the opposite
direction.
By the time we finish at the Potts'
house, the Bugler's house could be burnt
the ground.
All right, then. Well, we'll split up
and try to manage both fires at once. I
don't have a choice.
Just let the hose air out and everything
will be fine.
Fine? What about this mess?
What kind of fire department are you?
Took you long enough to get here.
We got here as quickly as we could, you
lady.
What I would like to know is just who is
in... In charge of the fire department.
In charge?
Well, no one, really.
Just as I thought.
Well, in the end, the emergency at Mrs.
Bugle's was a clogged chimney.
Oh, a typical.
That woman.
Oh, well, Hetty, now a clogged chimney
can be a fire hazard.
As is a clatterpot pot roast, I suppose.
the real thing.
Sorry, Alec, I didn't mean to laugh at
your ordeal.
Oh, no, and I, for one, think you're
performing a very important function in
community.
Thank you.
Now, Mrs. Bugle did make one good point,
that, well, someone's got to be in
charge of the fire department.
Well, it's obvious to me that you're the
man for the job.
I appreciate the endorsement, but you
may be a little biased.
Janet's merely pointing out that we
kings are all, after all, natural -born
leaders.
So, I rigged a rope from the top of the
lighthouse to the bell outside.
And when I see a fire, all I have to do
is pull a rope and the bell rings.
Gus, you're a genius.
Didn't I tell you you were the right man
for the job?
Could you hold this steady down here?
Of course.
Thank you.
Watch your thumb.
I have all the confidence in the world
in you.
Are you almost finished in here, Mr.
Pike?
Here, let me help, or you'll be here all
day.
Thank you, sir.
Becky, here it is.
Mr. Pike Frank.
Oh, my.
Very striking indeed.
Why on earth would he need a red jacket?
What is the fire chief's jacket?
Oh, I'm sure it's not finished yet. I
want to embroider something on the
like a fire chief.
Avonlea volunteer fire department.
Yes, but... It's too many words, isn't
it? I know.
I could shorten it to... Now, Janet,
listen. You mustn't go counting your
chickens before then.
Well, Alec hasn't been appointed fire
chief yet, you know. For heaven's sake,
nothing wrong with planning ahead?
Yes, I'm absolute.
So what are you ladies up to?
Nothing much.
Why does the little girl talk?
So why does it look like you're hiding
something?
Oh, Alec.
You know better than to pry.
All right, I'll go back to the barn and
work on the wagon.
Well, very nice.
And therefore, before we vote on who's
going to run the fire department...
I would like an explanation as to why it
took the fire department longer to
reach my house than Mrs. Potts.
Well, your house is further away than
Mrs. Potts. It looks like blatant
favoritism to me.
Are you saying that I got special
treatment?
Seems that way.
Well, if you've seen the mess they made
of my house, you wouldn't call it
favoritism. It's not my fault that you
like your pot roast so well done.
Really, Mrs. Bugle? Ladies, I think
we're digressing.
Let's get on with the business at hand.
At this time, the floor is now open for
nominations for the position of chief of
the Avonlea Volunteer Fire Department.
I nominate Alec King.
Is there a seconder?
Archie Gillis.
Alec, will you accept the nomination?
Oh, yes.
Yes, I do.
Are there any other nominations from the
floor?
I nominate Clive Pettibone.
Seconders?
Elvira, you can't be the seconder. You
nominated Alec King.
Thank you.
Mr. Pettibone, will you accept the
nomination?
With pleasure, Madam Chair.
Yes. Any further nominations?
Well, there we have it. The nominations
are closed.
Now, will the two nominees kindly wait
in the foyer, and we'll take it to a
vote.
Best of luck.
Same to you.
May the best man win.
All in favor of Alec King, raise your
hand.
Thank you.
All in favor of Mr. Pettibone, raise
your hand.
Well, the vote is even.
But someone hasn't voted.
Hetty King.
Yours is the deciding vote.
You can come back in now.
Now, both candidates are well
-qualified, splendid men, but we could
one fire chief.
Congratulations, Mr. Pettibone. You are
Avonlea's first fire chief.
Never would have believed it if I hadn't
seen it with my own eyes.
That man has absolutely turned her head.
You really should have done something
about this before. Now, after all, the
man's a soldier.
He's seen the world.
Lord knows what else.
Clive Pettibone is well qualified. I'm
sure he'll make an excellent chief.
I don't care about the fire department.
Talking about your sister, Hetty King,
was making a public fool of herself over
this man.
You know how Clara Potts and you lately
bugle like to prattle on.
Not to mention the fact that Clive
Pettibone is about as fit to be the
the fire department as I am.
In fact, I'm probably more qualified.
Felix!
Come and get it if you want it,
Felicity.
Felix,
what is this all about?
Father, I was just trying... Mother, he
took it.
It's all right, Felicity. Take it off,
Felix.
What are you wearing this for?
Well, Auntie Pettibone said her father
was going to be the new fire chief, so
you wouldn't have use for it.
She's not the only one who thinks so.
But I didn't believe her, Father.
What did I say, Mother?
Nothing, dear.
So here you are.
Well, now.
Oh, my.
So, how is the fire wagon coming along?
Oh, fine.
Oh, good.
Oh, Lord.
I've not set eyes on you for three days.
I've been busy.
You see, you know, Alec, Just because
you're not fire chief
doesn't mean you're not appreciated
around here.
It's not just the fire department. Ever
since Clive Pettibone came to town,
everybody seems to turn to him. I mean,
even my own children.
But you're still a father.
Mr. Pettibone's a teacher.
It's to be hoped the children would look
up to him.
Oh, I see. And what about you?
Me? Well, the two of you have been
spending an awful lot of time together.
I mean, even a fool could see that there
is something going on. Now, he is a
very worldly man. What am I supposed to
think?
You can think what you like, Alec King.
Whatever Mr.
Pettibone and I may choose to do
together is strictly our own business.
I don't go interfering with you and
Janet and your decision.
And I'll thank him.
Not to interfere with mine.
What are you two up to?
Science experiments.
Like the one Mr.
Pettibone did in class.
I thought you were very clever in
science today.
Well, not really.
Working with Pierre in the catching at
the hotel.
We have a lot of fires.
Nothing to get riled over.
Izzy, what are you doing?
Don't worry. I've got everything under
control.
You think this... Bucket, I will
demonstrate how to suffocate a fire.
You suffocate, Felix. You better do it
fast.
I don't think this is going to work.
But it worked for Mr. Pettibone in
class.
One of you better do something.
Oh, boy!
Mr. King.
You weren't at drill practice yesterday.
No, I was working on this pump for the
fire wagon.
Just about ready to test it.
I just wanted to make sure there was no
hard feeling between us.
Why should there be?
I'm glad you feel that way.
Your contribution to the fire department
is important.
I'm counting on your continued
participation.
In fact...
I need you.
I feel much better.
What I'm trying to do now is get the
operation organized.
My first concern is how to raise the
money so we can have a real steam
fire engine.
I don't see what's wrong with this pump
wagon. Once I've got it finished, it'll
be good enough for what we need.
It was an irrigation wagon, not a fire
wagon. It was an irrigation wagon. It's
now a fire wagon. Really, Mr. King, if
you ever did get it working, we couldn't
rely on it in an emergency.
If you think that, it shows you how
little you know, doesn't it?
At least I've had real firefighting
experience.
Let's face it, you were only elected
because you were able to persuade my
sister.
That machine of yours operational?
Can't guarantee it. It seems to me that
wagon's their only hope.
the pump with alec kane how'd you kill
it the hole i want everyone that died in
the fence fight from a bucket brigade
keep soaking the walls of the
we'll try to return the spread of the
flames for elicity sarah find the
keep out of the way
Does anybody here have any idea how this
got started?
It was a science experiment.
Fire is not something to be played with,
Felix. You know that.
We didn't think it was going to happen.
Honest. Someone could have been
seriously injured, Izzy. We're sorry.
We promise it won't happen again.
We'll discuss this further at home.
as you will, there's no one to hear you.
Pardon me, sir, or I shall reveal your
true nature to one and all.
And who would believe you?
No! No, no!
Hattie!
I must have been mistaken.
He's quite... I, uh... Well, I just
wanted to say... What
was all that?
I think your brother deserves the truth,
Miss King.
Well, yes, I suppose he does.
As a gentleman, allow me.
Mr. King, your sister and I are
collaborators.
Collaborators?
H -E -L -O -R.
King.
You?
I've been watching over her.
An excerpt from Serpents of the Golden
Tomb by C .L. Small.
C .L. Small.
Petty.
Oh, you both write books.
Ah.
Oh, I... I feel a complete... Oh.
Oh, no, Alec, you mustn't.
I think perhaps it was our fault for
trying to conceal the true nature of our
collusion.
You are my brother, after all.
Concerned for my welfare.
For that, I'm grateful. Oh, truly.
Thank you.
By the way, Mr. Pettibone.
You did a very good job today.
So did you, Mr. King.
Let's just hope the children learned a
lesson.
The children aren't the only ones who
learned something.
Here,
I thought you could use this. I was
going to leave it with Hedy.
You'll look good in it, Clive.
Thank you, Alec.
Splendid.
Alec.